Guide to the Department of Design and Environmental Analysis records, 1947-2007.
Department of Design and Environmental Analysis records, 1947-2007.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Department of Design and Environmental Analysis records, 1947-2007.
23-16-1472.
New York State College of Human Ecology. Design & Environmental Analysis.
4.3 Cubic Feet.; 10 oversize folders.
Syllabi, course materials, reports, drawings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library.
Oversize drawings from Professor Helen J. Cady's interior design classes in the Department of Design and Environmental Analysis at Cornell University.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
The Department of Design and Environmental Analysis was formerly known as the Department of Housing and Design.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Oversize drawings from Professor Helen J. Cady's interior design classes in the Department of Design and Environmental Analysis at Cornell University. Also annual reports for the Department of Housing and Design (1947-1962), newsletters (1949-1958) and plans (1963-1965).
SUBJECTS
Names:
New York State College of Human Ecology.; Cady, Helen J.; Interior architecture --Study and teaching.; Interior decoration --Study and teaching.; Cornell University --Faculty.; Cornell University. Dept. of Housing and Design.
Form and Genre Terms:
Drawings.; Videotapes.; Motion pictures (visual works).
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIAL
Additional material and digital versions can be found online here: http://ecommons.library.cornell.edu/handle/1813/11836
SERIES LIST
Series I. Reports; Faculty Annual Reports
Box 1; Box 2; Box 4- Folders: 15,17; Box 6- Folders: 5; Box 7- Folders: 1-51
Series II. Printed Material
Box 2; Box 4- Folders: 1-6; Box 6- Folder: 5
Series III. Course Material - Syllabi
Box 3- Folders: 1-40; Box 4- Folders: 6-11; Box 6- Folders: 3; Box 7- Folders: 2-8
Series IV. Department Reviews/Accreditation
Box 3- Folder: 31; Box 4- Folders: 12-14; Box 7- Folder: 1
Series V. Videotapes, Slides, Films
Box 6- Folders: 4
Series VI. Subject Files
Box 4- Folders: 16; Box 6- Folders: 2, 6-9
Series VII. Conferences
Box 6- Folders: 1
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Reports
  - Housing and design annual reports, 1947-1957 (Box 1)
  - Housing and design annual reports, 1958-1962 (Box 2)
  - Plans of work and reports, 1963-1965 (Box 2)
  - Gerontology project group (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Master plan for DEA, 1988-1998 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Department annual reports, 1980-1985 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Department annual reports, 1986-1988 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Department annual reports, 1989-1991 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Department annual reports, 1992-1995 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Department annual reports, 1998-1999; 2001-2006 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - DEA strategic plan, 2001-03 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Faculty Annual Reports
    See additional faculty reports in electronic format in collection #23-2-2817
    - Barker, Roger, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Becker, Franklin, 1981-1992 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Becker, Franklin, 1992-2005 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Beckman, Ronald, 1984-1992 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Boyd, Michael, 1980-1996 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Brittain, Bruce, 1985-1987 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Bushnell, Allen, 1966-1992 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Cukierski, Gwen, 1980-1983 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Danko, Sheila, 1984-2005 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - Elliott, Jack, 1999-2005 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Eshelman, Paul, 1981-2005 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - Evans, Gary W., 1992-1997 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - Evans, Gary W., 1997-2005 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - Garner, Clark, 1981-1991 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - Gibson, Kathleen, 1992-2005 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - Gilmore, Rhonda, 1995-2005 (Box 7, Folder 29)
    - Hedge, Alan, 1987-1994 (Box 7, Folder 30)
    - Hedge, Alan, 1994-2005 (Box 7, Folder 31)
    - Jennings, Jan, 1992-2005 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Laquatra, Joseph, 1984-1992 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Laquatra, Joseph, 1992-2005 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Mankowski, Leonard, 1980-1985 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Maxwell, Lorraine E., 1993-2003, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - McCarty, James, 1987-1991 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Meneely, Jason, 2004-2005 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Millican, Cory, 1980-1990 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Ostrander, Edward, 1967-1991 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Pierce, Mark, 1997-2005 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Rector, Regina, 1980-1984 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Schrank, Elliot, 1992-1997 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Sims, William Riley, 1988-1996 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Sims, William Riley, 1996-2005 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Sloan, Gary, 1981-1985 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Straight, Clara, 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Wells, Nancy, 2001-2005 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Williams, Christopher, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Worth, Stan W., 1981-1983 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Yackel, Christine M., 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 51)
- Series II. Printed Material
  - Housing and Design newsletters, 1949-1958 (Box 2)
  - DEA extension newsletter, 1970-1971 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - DEA extension newsletter, 1971-1973 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - DEA extension newsletter, 1974-1975 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Textile Update, 1975-1976 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - DEA quarterly newsletter, 1974-1978 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - DEA News-Cooperative extension publication of the DEA department, 1979-03-1979-11 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - DEA News, 1980-1982 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - DEA News, 1983-1985 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - DEA News, 1985, 1989, 1991, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - DEA Monthly Housing newsletter, 1981-1982 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - "Knit Sport Jacket" by Jean McLean and Madeline Blum, 1970-1979 (Box 4, 4A)
  - "Threads"-volume 1 #1-8, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Housing fact sheets, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Newsletter - "Housing ans Home Environment News", 1994-2001 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Newsletter - "Housing and Home Environment News", 1989-1991, 1993 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Resources, policy and procedures manual, 1996-1997, 1999-2000, 2000-2001 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Publicity material concerning the department and faculty, 1981-2003 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Article about DEA from "Interior Design", 1995-08 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Series III. Course Material - Syllabi
  - Professor Helen Cady's 325 and 326 three-five week interior design course - includes lighting study unit projects by students Nancy Williams, Ruth Morgan, Zipporah Stambler and S. King, 1962 (Folder 7)
  - DEA 261, Fundamentals of Interior Design Studio Problems (Folder 9)
  - Bound copy of DEA syllabi for the year, 1998-1999 (Box 3)
  - Proposed changes in interior design curriculum, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Course 101, 1980-1995 (Box 3, Folder 1A)
  - Course 102, 1980-2000 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Course 104, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Course 111, 1988-1997 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Courses 114, 117 and 143, 1990-1993 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Courses 114, 117 and 143, 1980-1992 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Courses 114, 117 and 143, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Course 115, 1979-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Course 150, 1981-1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Course 150, 1996-2002, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Course 150 - Exams, 1980-1999 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Course 201, 1980-2002, 2006, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Course 202, 1980-1995, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Course 203, 1987-1992, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Course 204, 1990-1995; 2006, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Course 204 - Exams, 1987-2001 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Course 210, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Course 250, 1982-2000 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Course 251, 1984-2000; 2005 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Courses 252, 261, 301, 1985-1995 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Course 302, 1985-2001 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Course 303, 1989-1997; 2006 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Courses 305, 1995, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Courses 310, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Course 325, 1986-1999, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Courses 343, 348, 1987-1999 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Course 349, 1980s-1996 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Course 350, 1981-1993 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Course 353, 1976-1993 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Course 404, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Courses 401, 443, 453, 1995-1996, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Course 454, 1989-2000 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Course 455, 1980-1992 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Course 455, 1993-2001 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Course 455 -handouts (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Course 459, 1982-1997, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Course 460, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Course 499, 1979-1993 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Courses 468, 640, 1998, 1980-1989 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Course 643, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Course 643, 1987-1999 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Course 648, 1987-1997 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Course 650, 1981-1995 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Course 651, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Course 652, 1988-1994 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Course 653, 1991-1996 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Course 654, 1993-1997, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Course 659, 1987-1997, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Course 668, 1986-1997, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Course 670, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Course 671, 1995, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Course 319 - The Child Oriented Environment (1973) and Course 417 - Workshop in Environmental Design (1975) - Professor Coates, 1973, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Course 375 - Residential Environments - The Behavioral Basis for Design Decisions - Professor Coates, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Course 219 - Design Methods: Planning Strategies - Professor Coates, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Course 150 - Human and Social Factors - Professor Coates, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Field study course - Designing Clothing - Professor Yackel, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Contemporary House Analyses, 1982-10 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Courses 1101, 1110, 2010, 2500, 2510, 3030, 3250, 4070, 4550, 6510, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Fall
  - Course 241 and 242, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Course 243, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Course 304, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    Spring
  - Course 407, 2006 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Course 423 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Courses 201, 250/660, 251, 459/660, 2007 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Courses 115, 150, 202, 203, 204, 305, 350, 408, 410, 415, 422, 470, 652, 645, 668, 670, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Poster designed by Sheila Danko's students where they found the letters of the alphabet in the built environment and nature, 1997 (Folder 1)
  - Banner using Cornell's charter (with Cornell 1865 in red words) designed by Rhonda Gilmore's students for Cornell's sesquicentennial, 2015 (Map-case O-9)
- Series IV. Department Reviews/Accreditation
  - New York State 4-H clothing and textiles program: A review conducted by Gret Atkin, 1982 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Foundation for interior design education research accreditation report, 1990 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - FIDER - Program evaluation report, 2002 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - FIDER - Program evaluation report, 1994-1995 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - FIDER - Program evaluation report, required appendix materials, 1994 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - FIDER - Accreditation report, 1995-03 (Box 4, Folder 14A)
  - Correspondence regarding the termination of the MPS degree in interior design, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Series V. Videotapes, Slides, Films
  - "Home Builders Institute: Talking Trash", V-692
  - "Healthy Indoor Air for America's Homes", V-693
  - "Building a Home Buyers Educational Program" Tape 1, V-694
  - "Building a Home Buyers Educational Program" Tape 2, V-695
  - "Building a Home Buyers Educational Program" Tape 3, V-696
  - "Building a Home Buyers Educational Program" slide show used for admissions (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 29-8mm Department flammability films, some labeled Betsy Anderson's study, 1967-1970s (Box 8)
- Series VI. Subject Files
  - Advisory council members, 1991-1995 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Computer-aided design (CAD) labs- DEA And FSAD, 2007-12 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Advisory council, 1988-1997 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Advisory council, 1998-1999 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Advisory council, 2000-2006 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Advisory council - slides, 1995-1998 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, memos concerning the department, 1983-2000 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Organizational chart (1997); ABC project (1997); International Workplace Studies Program -Workscape 21 (1996-1998) (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Series VII. Conferences
  - Housing Education and Research Association Annual Conference "HERA's 40th anniversary:Celebrating Our Past With A Look To The Future" - Conference proceedings, 2006-10 (Box 6, Folder 1)